A Guide to the United Daughters of the Confederacy, Turner Ashby Chapter Records, 1896-1991: SC 0121
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
United Daughters of the Confederacy, Turner Ashby Chapter Records
1896-1991
Special Collections, James Madison University
United Daughters of the Confederacy. Turner Ashby Chapter
SC 0121
2.42 cubic feet; 3 boxes, 9 audiocassettes
This collection deals with the records from the Turner Ashby Chapter of the United Daughters of the Confederacy. These records are mostly comprised of membership applications dated 1896-1991, along with memorabilia such as confederate banners, scrapbooks, yearbooks, cassette tapes, and the original charters for the chapter.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this collection.
Acquisition Information
Placed on deposit through contract with the Turner Ashby Chapter of the United Daughters of the Confederacy dated November 7, 1989 with additions in March 1991 and February 1993.
Administrative History
The United Daughters of the Confederacy were formed by the outgrowth of local and memorial groups related the United Confederate Veterans, formed after the Civil War. It was first founded in Nashville, Tennessee on September 10, 1894 under the name the National Association of the Daughters of the Confederacy. At its second meeting in Atlanta, Georgia, in 1895, the name of the organization was changed to the United Daughters of the Confederacy. Membership into a chapter of the UDC requires that women applying must be at least 16 years of age who are lineal or collateral blood descendants of men and women who served in the Army, Navy, or Civil Service for the Confederate States during the Civil War. On October 21, 1895, four chapters charted by the UDC met in Alexandria, Va. and organized the first statewide organization with the UDC: the Virginia Division. The Turner Ashby Chapter was chartered by about two dozen Harrisonburg women in the late 1890s. Today, the chapter has taken on a variety of education and historic preservation efforts, especially the Turner Ashby monument.
Scope and Content
The United Daughters of the Confederacy, Turner Ashby Chapter Records, 1896-1990s, consists of 1 Hollinger box and 2 flat boxes containing the records of the chapter up until the present day. These records are mainly comprised of membership application forms, along with some incomplete forms and several Confederate banners. In the accompanying flat boxes, there are the original charters, programs, yearbooks, and scrapbooks.
There are also 9 cassette tapes with recordings of the proceedings of the Centennial celebration of the Stonewall Jackson Valley Campaign events, held in 1962, as well as other events hosted by the UDC. The recordings include interviews with local persons, including Dr. John Wayland and Rev. John G. Dubosq, by local radio personality Wip Robinson. The Mr. Robinson's wife Jane was a very active chapter president. An index to the tapes is available in Box 1.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in the following three series:
Series 1: Membership Applications, 1896-1991
Series 2: Memorabilia, 1896-1989
Series 2: Sound Recordings, 1960-1968, undated
Related Material
United Daughters of the Confederacy, Southern Cross of Honor Records, 1905-1941, SC 0097, Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University, Harrisonburg, Va.
Bibliography
"Historical - Educational - Benevolent - Memorial - Patriotic." United Daughters of the Confederacy. Accessed September 2013. http://hqudc.org/.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Ashby, Turner, 1828-1862 -- Monuments; United Daughters of the Confederacy. Turner Ashby Chapter, No. 162 (Harrisonburg, Va.) -- Records and correspondence; Confederate States of America -- History -- Societies, etc.; Confederate States of America. Army -- History; Confederate States of America. Army -- Flags; Confederate States of America -- History, Military -- Sources; United States -- Armed Forces -- History; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Sources; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Societies, etc. -- Confederate; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Flags; Confederate States of America -- History -- Sources; Virginia -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Sources; Shenandoah River Valley (Va. and W. Va.) -- History -- Sources; Shenandoah River Valley (Va. and W. Va.) -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Sources; Mountain people -- Virginia -- Shenandoah National Park -- Social life and customs
- Series 1: Membership Applications, 1896-1991, undated
  - Membership Applications, Oldest Records, 1896-1904 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Membership Applications, 1904-1910 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Membership Applications, 1910-1913 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Membership Applications, 1913-1923 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Membership Applications, 1923-1925 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Membership Applications, 1925-1934 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Membership Applications, 1935-1952 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Membership Applications, 1954-1989 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Active file (as of March 1991), 1991 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Members, Associates, and Incomplete forms, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Series 2: Memorabilia, 1896-1989
  - Confederate Banners, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Programs, 1912-1989 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Index to cassette tapes, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Scrapbook, 1960-1961 (Box OV 1)
  - Scrapbook, 1962 (Box OV 1)
  - Charters, 1896-1897 (Box OV 2, Folder 1)
  - Yearbooks, 1940-1987 (Box OV 2)
    Scope and Contents
    Contains yearbooks for 1940/41-1951/52, 1953/54-1956, 1958/59, 1959/60, 1961, 1962/63, 1973/74- 1975/76,1978/79, 1981/82-1982/83, 1986/87
  - Scrapbook, 1988-1989 (Box OV 2)
- Series 3: Sound Recordings, ca. 1960-1968
  The series is comprised of 13 recordings, captured on 9 audiocassette tapes that document various events hosted by the United Daughters of the Confederacy, as well as activities of Jane Robinson, President of the Turner Ashby Chapter of the UDC, and her husband Wip Robinson, a radio personality in the Harrisonburg area.
  - SC0121-1: Role of Women in the South, Turner Ashby Chapter of the United Daughters of the Confederacy, ca. 1961 (Digital-materials SC0121-SET-001)
    Speech by unidentified person, given to the Turner Ashby Chapter of the United Daughters of the Confederacy, regarding the "women of the south," specifically Richmond, Virginia. Side A.
    - Preservation master audiocassette, ca. 1961 (Box 1, Audiocassette SC0121-CS-001)
  - SC0121-2: John Wayland interviewed by Wip Robinson, undated (Digital-materials SC0121-SET-001)
    Dr. John Wayland interviewed by Wip Robinson. Topics include James W. Marshall ("Cyclone Jime"); the oldest town in the Shenandoah Valley; the "German Regiment" led by Abraham Bowland of the Shenandoah Valley; Powell'ss Fort in Massanutten, and the origin of its name; the location and history of Shawnee Springs; The history of the courthouse in Woodstock; the old log church where Muhlenberg and Asbury gave sermons; the Bloody Ford; the story of the John Rhodes family "killed by Indians;" Crany Island; the iron foundry, flour mill and saw mill (Abraham Bird); the Stony Man and Hawksbill Head, Blue Ridge Mountain Range. Side B.
    - Preservation master audiocassette, undated (Box 1, Audiocassette SC0121-CS-001)
  - SC0121-3: Reverand John G. Dubosq interviewed by Wip Robinson, March 5, 1968 (Digital-materials SC0121-SET-001)
    Interview with Reverand John G. Dubosq, by Wip Robinson, conducted at the Jollett Hollow Chapel. Dubosq discusses his personal history and the establishment of the Skyline Drive Park. Discusses his work as a singer in blackface as a member of the quartet, Penn City Comedy Four; work as a minister in the Jollet Hollow Mission Church in Jollett Hollow, Page County, Virginia; moonshining and moonshiners; his work at the the church and establishing a men's fellowship; parishioners donating food; recreation in the Blue Ridge Mountains; the impact of the construction of Skyline Drive on people living on the moutain; the settlement communities displaced residents of the Shenandoah National Park.
    - Preservation master audiocassette, March 5, 1968 (Box 1, Audiocassette SC0121-CS-002)
  - SC0121-4: "Noontime Almanac" with Wip Robinson, WSVA Harrisonburg, Virginia, undated (Digital-materials SC0121-SET-001)
    Wip Robinson host of the "Noontime "Almanac," on WSHV in Harrisonburg, Virginia, discusses agriculture in Shenandoh County, including poultry reports, and steer and cattle prices in Harrisonburg; interviews Bill Clark of Hardy County, West Virginia, who discusses agriculture in that area. Side A.
    - Preservation master audiocassette, undated (Box 1, Audiocassette SC0121-CS-003)
  - SC0121-5: 1st Annual picnic of Virginia DABS, Wip Robinson, undated (Digital-materials SC0121-SET-001)
    Wip Robinson interviews attendees of the 1st Annual Picnic of Virginia DABS. He asks people their name, city of residence, and the color of their mailboxes. Side B. August 7, 1962?
    - Preservation master audiocassette, undated (Box 1, Audiocassette SC0121-CS-003)
  - SC0121-6: Centennial Celebration of Stonewall Jackson Valley Campaign Re-March and Reenactment, Elkton, Virginia, April 28, 1962 (Digital-materials SC0121-SET-001)
    Recording of the "kick-off" event held to commemorate a remarch of the Stonewall Jackson's Valley Campaign route; Speech about the Stonewall Brigade given by Dr. William G. Bean, professor at William and Mary. The event took place in Elkton, Virginia, referred to by it's former name, Conrad's Store.
    - Preservation master audiocassette, April 28, 1962 (Box 1, Audiocassette SC0121-CS-004)
  - SC0121-7: Speech by James "Bud" I. Robertson, Centennial Celebration of Stonewall Jackson Valley Campaign, March 22, 1962 (Digital-materials SC0121-SET-001)
    Probably occurred Thursday, March 22, 1962.
    - Preservation master audiocassette, March 22, 1962 (Box 1, Audiocassette SC0121-CS-005)
    - Preservation master audiocassette, March 22, 1962 (Box 1, Audiocassette SC0121-CS-006)
  - SC0121-8: Virginia DABS Fall Picnic at Massanutten Caverns, Wip Robinson, undated (Digital-materials SC0121-SET-001)
    Wip Robinson interviews attendees of a fall picnic at Massanutten Caverns. Robinson asks people their name and place of residence, and the color of the their mailbox.
    - Preservation master audiocassette, undated (Box 1, Audiocassette SC0121-CS-006)
  - SC0121-9: Turner Ashby Monument Dedication, presided by Jane Robinson, June 9, 1962 (Digital-materials SC0121-SET-001)
    The program included comments by Frances B. Ryan of Emannuel Episcopal Church, Mayor of Harrionsburg, Frank C. Switzer who welcoms the marchers, Dabney W. Watts, the Chairman of the Shenandoah Valley Civil War Centennial Committee, and Rober Frazier and the Harrisonburg High School Band playing "Dixie." The event is hosted by Jane Robinson, president of the Turner Ashby Chapter of the United Daughters of the Confederacy. Side A.
    - Preservation master audiocassette, June 9, 1962 (Box 1, Audiocassette SC0121-CS-007)
  - SC0121-10: Speech about Sidney Lanier, Turner Ashby Chapter of the United Daughters of the Confederacy, undated (Digital-materials SC0121-SET-001)
    Speech given by an unnamed woman on the life of Sidney Lanier. Side B.
    - Preservation master audiocassette, undated (Box 1, Audiocassette SC0121-CS-007)
  - SC0121-11: Tribute to Jane Robinson, "Here's History" Radio Show with Dick McGrath, February 2, 1964 (Digital-materials SC0121-SET-001)
    Side A.
    - Preservation master audiocassette, February 2, 1964 (Box 1, Audiocassette SC0121-CS-008)
  - SC0121-12: "Reminiscing with Jane" Radio Show, with Wip Robinson, ca. 1962 (Digital-materials SC0121-SET-001)
    Refers to Jane Robinson recovering from an illness. Side B.
    - Preservation master audiocassette, ca. 1962 (Box 1, Audiocassette SC0121-CS-008)
  - SC0121-13: Unknown Speaker and Singer, undated (Digital-materials SC0121-SET-001)
    Musical program of unidentified singer.
    - Preservation master audiocassette, undated (Box 1, Audiocassette SC0121-CS-009)